<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true copies of tvvo especiall letters verbatim sent from the Palatinate by Sir, F.N. relating the dangerous incounter which hapened betwixt the Duke Christian of Brunswicke, and Monsieur Tillies passing ouer the bridge lying vpon the riuer Mayne about Ausbourge. VVith the vniting of his forces with the King of Bohemias, as also the fearefull expectation of the great Turkes comming downe into Germanie. With the late proceedings in the Low Countries, in their proclamations set forth by the States of Holland, the first shewing the last appointed time, as well for forrayners as inhabitants of this countrey to come into the West India Company of the Nether-lands: the second a letter of Marte, the last prohibiting the inhabitants not to assuer any goods of the Spaniards. Printed this 21. of Iune.</title>
            <author>Nethersole, Francis, Sir, 1587-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.55</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845692</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10610</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10610)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1211:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true copies of tvvo especiall letters verbatim sent from the Palatinate by Sir, F.N. relating the dangerous incounter which hapened betwixt the Duke Christian of Brunswicke, and Monsieur Tillies passing ouer the bridge lying vpon the riuer Mayne about Ausbourge. VVith the vniting of his forces with the King of Bohemias, as also the fearefull expectation of the great Turkes comming downe into Germanie. With the late proceedings in the Low Countries, in their proclamations set forth by the States of Holland, the first shewing the last appointed time, as well for forrayners as inhabitants of this countrey to come into the West India Company of the Nether-lands: the second a letter of Marte, the last prohibiting the inhabitants not to assuer any goods of the Spaniards. Printed this 21. of Iune.</title>
                  <author>Nethersole, Francis, Sir, 1587-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones [and Edward Allde] for Nicholas Bourne and Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at the Royall Exchange, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sir, F.N. = Sir Francis Nethersole.</note>
                  <note>Quire C was apparently printed by Edward Allde (Dahl).</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18328 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:1"/>
            <p>THE TRVE COPIES OF TVVO ESPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIALL LETTERS VERBATIM SENT FROM THE PALATINATE BY SIR. <hi>F. N.</hi> Relating the dangerous incounter which hapened <hi>betwixt the Duke</hi> Chriſtian <hi>of</hi> Brunſwicke, <hi>and</hi> Monſieur <hi>Tillies</hi> paſſing ouer the bridge lying <hi>vpon the riuer Mayne about</hi> Ausbourge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith the vniting of his forces with the King of Bohemias,</hi> as alſo the fearefull expectation <hi>of the great</hi> Turkes <hi>comming downe</hi> into <hi>Germanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the late proceedings in the Low Countries, <hi>in their Proclamations ſet forth by the States of</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the firſt ſhewing the laſt appointed time, as well <hi>for forrayners as inhabitants of this Countrey to come into</hi> the <hi>Weſt India</hi> Company of the <hi>Nether-lands:</hi> the ſecond a letter of Marte, the laſt prohibiting the inhabitants not to aſſuer any goods of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed this 21. of Iune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>William Iones</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Royall Exchange, and in Popes-head Alley. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:2"/>
            <head>A COPIE OF THE FIRST LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wrote to you at large on Sunday laſt and haue little to adde ſince, but am like to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough very ſhortly, I pray God it proue good. The Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> was foure dayes ſince at <hi>Nidda</hi> in the land of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> about fiue leagues from <hi>Francfort.</hi> Mounſuor <hi>Tilly</hi> &amp;c. are gone towards him, and if they be once on the ſame ſide of the Mayne, there will in all likely hood be blowes between them. Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> is not gone to the <hi>Griſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> but doth now aſſemble his forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, vvith deſſeigne as vve iudge to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10610:3"/>
               <hi>Hagenaw</hi> againe, or elſe to fall downe to ioyne vvith his party, neither of vvhich muſt be ſuffered by the Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and he is likely therfore to go to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke we hope to morrow, for as yet he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth betweene the two riuers by the towne, and is not himſelfe well able to ſtand. This is all we haue here.</p>
            <p>From <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna</hi> we haue that the Diot of <hi>Hungarie</hi> goeth not on the Emperours mind, and that the Turk is like to giue'vs peace here, we haue ſmall ſignes of one elſe, and that is a bad one. The King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to obey his father, is minded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his mind to ſtay here or at <hi>Heydel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> in expectation of the iſſue of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at <hi>Bruſſels. Manheim</hi> the 6. of Iune.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10610:3"/>
            <head>A Copie of the ſecond Letter.</head>
            <p>IN my laſt Letter you know that <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Tilly</hi> was then marching towards the Duke <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> then in the land of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> not farre from <hi>Frankford.</hi> The Duke ſoone after tooke <hi>Hoeſt</hi> a towne and caſtle of the Elector of <hi>Ments,</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon the Mayne before <hi>Frankford,</hi> vvhere he had newes that <hi>Tilly</hi> and <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſales</hi> ioyned and marched to him ouer the Mayne at <hi>Aſchburg</hi> vvith an army of 40. m. as was giuen out, I thinke not much leſſe then 30. m. yet he reſolued to abide it rather then the hazard of a retrait. And they thereupon marched on furiouſly by <hi>Hanaw</hi> and <hi>Frankford.</hi> The Duke in the meane time prouided himſelfe the beſt he could to receiue them, ſeeing on the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of the ground, intrenching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and burning the villages by which the enemy vvere to march to him. This done, he ſent hether to the Count of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10610:4"/>
               <hi>Mansfeld,</hi> to let him know in what poſhire he ſtood, and that he would doe the beſt he could to hold himſelfe ſo, till the Count might march to him, for whoſe paſſage, or his owne retreate if he were forced to it, prepared to make a Bridge ouer the <hi>Mayne,</hi> This newes came to the Counte <hi>Mansfield</hi> as Hee was Marching ouer the Rhyne, with deſſeigne to haue gone to breake the bridge at <hi>Oppenheim,</hi> or that fayling, to haue made ſome other diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on that ſide, thereby to haue eaſed the Duke of <hi>Brunſwyck,</hi> by giuing <hi>Gonzales</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to looke backward. But herevpon Hee the ſame inſtant commaunded ſixtie troupes of horſe to march ouer the Neccar towards the Duke intending to haue follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed himſelfe with the reſt of his army this day. But we haue this morning newes, that the Duke was beaten yeſterday. The maner and meaſure of it. is yet variouſly related, but I hope to adde it to this before I cloſe it. In the meane to doe all I may, againſt the ſuddayne diſpatch of the poſt, I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely take leaue reſt.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10610:4"/>
I muſt cloſe this Letter and yet haue no more certaintie of the defeat of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> but that hee never gaue Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but having beene extreamly moleſted by the Enemies Cannon, who had twelue peeces at leaſt, whereas the Duke had but two: through ſome confuſion among his men hee was forced to retire ouer the Bridge he had made over the Maine, by the breaking whereof, many of his foote were drowned, others cut off being hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by carriages, they all are loſt as well of baggage as munition, ſaving the Dukes owne wagons, wherein his money was, His Horſe eſcaped well, ſome ouer the Bridge, other are forced ouer the deepe that they were put to Swimme, by which meanes ſome number of them alſo are loſt, and among them the Count <hi>Leneſtlin</hi> who married Miſtreſſe <hi>Dudly,</hi> thought to bee one, the number can not yet be eſtimated, but divers came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not beleeue there were aboue one thouſand men loſt, yet I doubt more, The reſt are retyring through the <hi>Bergſtrate</hi> hither in great confuſion, and I doubt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10610:5"/>moſt of the foote will haue caſt away their Armes, which is a great vnrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loſſe, whether the Enemie doe purſue them on this ſide the Mayne or no, is not yet knowne here, But to be ſure the Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> hath drawne out his whole Armie into the <hi>Berge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> who being freſh we may redeeme loſſe if the Enemie do follow, the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is for himſelfe ſafe for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and extreamely diſcontented that he fought not.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Mainheim <date>the 11. of Iune 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10610:5"/>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION OF THE HIGH AND MIGHTY LORDS, THE STATES GENERALL of the vnited <hi>Provinces,</hi> whereby is prohibited <hi>vnto the Merchants, and Inhabitants</hi> of thoſe Countries, not to make any aſſurances of goods, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, or ſhips belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any Subiects of <hi>the King of</hi> Spaine, <hi>or Enemies of</hi> theſe Lands.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He States Generall of the vnited Provinces to all them that ſee or heare theſe read gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. VVhereas Wee haue beene certainly informed, that divers. Merchants and inhabitants of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10610:6"/>(notwithſtanding We after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of the Truce, are compelled to incounter the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, in all hoſtile manner) to aſſure the goods, Merchandiſes, and ſhips, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto the Subiects and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and other enemies of theſe Landes: Whereby it happens, that the ſayd goods and ſhips being taken by Our men of Warre, or thoſe that haue Commiſſion of Vs to endammage the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> or his Subiects, the ſayd Aſſurances and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities, claime and follow them as if they were their owne, to haue them releaſed: And beſides, the ſayd being declared good Priſes and forfeited, the dammage doth not light vpon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies aforeſayd, but vpon the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes of theſe Countries, by the meanes of the aforeſayd aſſurance and ſecuritie, who enioy but a ſmall reward or profit for the ſame, In ſuch manner that the Inhabitantes of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and not Our Enemies heereby are impoveriſhed, being the fame likewiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10610:6"/>very hurtfull to the equipations and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of Ships, which many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of thoſe Countries with more minde and zeale would make other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe againſt Our Enemies, which now are kept backe in regard of the recla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and purſuings of ſuch aſſured goods.</p>
            <p>Now to prevent the ſame and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this conveniently, We haue directly forbidden and interdicted, forbid and interdict by theſe Preſents, all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and other Inhabitants of theſe Provinces, neyther directly nor indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to aſſure any goods, Merchandiſes, or Ships, of whatſoever Fort or kinde the ſayd may be appertaining to any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> or his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, in any manner whatſoever: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring all and euery one of ſuch Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances made, or here after to be made for nought, and of no value.</p>
            <p>Prohibiting likewiſe all Iuſtices, Courts, Commiſſioners of the Courts of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or other whom this may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, to giue iudgement of ſuch Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10610:7"/>And here beſides the Aſſurances, that ſhall be found to haue made ſuch Aſſurances ſince this day, ſhall forfeit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery ſumme ſmall or bigge, that they ſhall haue ſigned, hundreth pounds Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, one halfe to the Informer, and the other halfe to the officer to be payd that ſhall doe the execution.</p>
            <p>And becauſe none here after ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ignorance, We require, and intreat the States, the Governours, the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Counſells, and the States of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue Provinces of <hi>Gelderland, Zutphen, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſtvrieſland, Sealand, Vtrecht, Vrieſland, Overyſſell,</hi> the Cittie <hi>Groeringen,</hi> and the Lands about it, and all other Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices and Officers, whom this may touch, that they Commannd this Our Order preſently to bee Proclaimed and Publiſhed where it is vſuall, Proceeding and cauſing to bee proceeded againſt the Tranſgreſſors and offenders of the ſame, without any favour diſſimulation or compoſition, ſeeing wee finde it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the good of theſe Lands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:10610:7"/>
This concluded in the meeting of the High and mighty the Lords States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall aforeſayd, at the <hi>Hage</hi> the firſt of Aprill, Anno 1622. Was ſubſcribed <hi>A Ploos.</hi> And lower was written, at the Order of High and Mighty Lords the States Generall, ſigned</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. Aerſſens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:8"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:10610:8"/>
            <head>VVARNING CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE WEST INDIA Companie of the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Committees appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to collect a ſtock for the <hi>Weſt India</hi> Company, in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Sealand,</hi> being au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized thereunto by the States of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, make knowne by theſe: That beſides other aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, it is graunted vnto the ſaid Company by the High and mighty Lords, the States Generall of the vnited Prouinces, to trafficke onely for Salt at <hi>Punto del Key.</hi> And that the laſt time prefixed for the Inhabitants of the vnited Prouinces, to come in the ſaid Company, is the laſt of Iuly <hi>ſtile now,</hi> and for Forraigners the laſt of September following, both incluſiue, and according to the new ſtile. Wherefore if there bee any that will participate in the ſaid Company, let them direct
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10610:9"/>themſelues vnto the Committees, appointed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cities, and deliuer there their Signatures and ſubſcriptions of ſuch ſummes, as they ſhall be deſirous to participate in the ſaid Companies, which are to be payed in three payments: <hi>viz.</hi> a third part at the expiration of the aforeſaid time: and the other two third parts in three next following yeares, vnleſſe afterwards at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall meeting of the Aſſiſtants or Committees, it be thought fit to prolong the ſaid Payments for any longer time, in which caſe the Participants ſhall be warned by bils affixed. And after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of the time aforeſaid, ſhall none be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the ſaid Company. Giuing notice beſides, that according to the reſolution of the Lords, the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and Weſt <hi>Freeſland,</hi> the chiefe Participants of the Company, ſhall be qualified to be Aſſiſtants, in this manner, that thoſe who in the Chamber of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> ſhall for themſelues bring in the ſumme of ſixe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and in the reſpectiue Chambers about the Maſe, and in the Northerne parts foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Karelies Gilders, ſhall haue power to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate three, for to chooſe out of them (according to the Patent) the Aſſiſtants. Item that the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>Holland</hi> where are no Chambers, and ſhall be brought in vpon one name, an hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Gilders, ſhall haue power to appoint an aſſiſtant after precedent denomination, and to put him in any of the other Chambers. And after
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10610:9"/>the expiration of the aforeſaid laſt of Iuly (agree. to the Patent) ſhall be preſently proceeded to the election of the Aſſiſtants, to goe immediatly in hand with the equipation and octroyed Nauigation. This done, the tenth of Iune, in the yeare of our Lord, 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:10"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:10610:10"/>
            <head>A Letter of Mart, Graunted by the Lords States Generall, to them of the Vnited Prouinces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y theſe preſents is Giuen notice, and made knowne vnto euery one out of the Name of the High and Mighty Lords, the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Vnited Prouinces, That whoſoeuer (to endamage the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> his Adherents and Subiects, aſwell of <hi>Spaine, Portingall, Brabant, Flaunders,</hi> as alſo other places being in his Dominions) ſhall be deſirous vpon a due and fit Commiſſion to ſet any Ship or Ships at Sea to goe vpon free Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they ſhall henceforth pay no more, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept otherwiſe be ordered, then Eighteene in the Hundred, whereas they did pay heere before Thirty in hundred, which the Country and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> as Admirall of the Sea out of the Prizes were vſed to Inioy as their right, whereof Twelue ſhall bee for the Countrey, and Sixe for the Prince aboue mentioned. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10610:11"/>an equall order may be kept concerning the putting in of Security, euery one that ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to goe vpon Conditions aforeſaid, ſhall bee bound to put in Security in the Court of the Admiralty of the place from whence they intend to depart, for Ten Thouſand Gilders, which is 1000. pounds Sterling, and that aboue the Ship and what therein, with action ſhall ſerue onely to giue ſecurity that the Court prizes to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſuch a Ship ſhall be brought in to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in the Colledge of the Admiralty, where the ſecurity hath beene giuen, which being done, the Securities ſhall be Diſcharged, Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that if the ſaid Ship goes afterwards with like Commiſſion, there muſt be put in new Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, And if any body ſhall pretend that hee is wrongfully Damnified, hee may enter his Action againſt the Captaine, and thoſe that haue Indamaged him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10610:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
